A Finding Aid to the Violet Oakley Papers, 1841-1981, in the Archives of American Art AAA.oaklviol
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1857-1979; Series 2; 26.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-30
  - Chronological, 1973-1979 (Box 30, Folder 10-20)
- Notes and Writings, 1899-1976; Series 3; 10.6 Linear feet Boxes 30-38, 58-64, OV 66, OV 70
  Materials are arranged chronologically within document types.
  Notes and writings consist of essays, event schedules, lectures and speeches, performances, literary writings, publication drafts, writings by others, and substantial chronological and miscellaneous writings. There are also project files containing writings and notes related to 16 of her major artworks, including her interest in historic figures ranging from William Penn to Jane Addams, her commissioned work for the Vassar Alumni and Charlton Yarnell houses, her work on the League of Nations portfolio, and writings related to her murals for the Pennsylvania Capitol Senate, Supreme Court, and Governor's reception chambers. These include multiple drafts and gallery proofs for her publications The Holy Experiment, The Law Triumphant, and The Geneva Drawings.
  - Essays, 1915-1955; 3.1
    - "Casket Containing the Gold Medal of the Philadelphia Award", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - "Constance Armfield", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - "Essays I Have Never Written", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - [Landing of Pilgrims], circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - "Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - "Venetian Notes", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 26)
    - "Support of the Monitor", 1916 (Box 30, Folder 27)
    - "George de Forest Brush", 1921 (Box 30, Folder 28)
    - "Armistice Day" (for American Peace Award), 1923 (Box 30, Folder 29)
    - "Fullness of God", 1936 (Box 30, Folder 30)
    - On Christian Science, 1936 (Box 30, Folder 31)
    - "Fresco Painters of Italy", 1939 (Box 30, Folder 32)
    - "Modern Revival of Fresco as a Medium", 1939 (Box 30, Folder 33)
    - "Fresco Painters of Italy" and "Modern Revival of the Medium", 1939 (Box 30, Folder 34)
  - Events, 1915-1957; 3.2
    - Engagement List for Olga Detarnowsky, circa 1915-1930 (Box 30, Folder 35)
    - Engagement List for Ruth St. Denis, circa 1915-1930 (Box 30, Folder 36)
    - Viewing of "Portrait of a Debutante", 1941 (Box 30, Folder 37)
    - Woodmere Exhibition, 1942 (Box 30, Folder 38)
    - Drexel Institute Commencement, 1948 (Box 30, Folder 39)
    - Lehigh Exhibition, 1951 (Box 30, Folder 40)
    - "Berry Notebook of a Pilgrim", 1951 (Box 30, Folder 41)
    - Loans to the Harrisburg Public Library, 1955 (Box 30, Folder 42)
    - Pictures for High Oaks Exhibition, 1955 (Box 30, Folder 43)
    - Washington, D.C. Exhibition, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 44)
  - Lectures and Speeches, 1911-1955; 3.3
    - "Architectonic Painting", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 45)
    - Cogslea Academy Discussion Series, circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 46)
    - "Illustration in a Machine Age", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 47)
    - "Philadelphia Portraits and Portrait Painters", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 48)
    - "Save the Orchestra", circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 49)
    - Speech for Conshohocken Art League, circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 50)
    - Speech for Women's International League, circa 1915-1955 (Box 30, Folder 51)
    - "A Declaration to be Read July 4th, 1911" (Box 30, Folder 52)
    - Lecture Notes, 1914-1916 (Box 30, Folder 53-54)
    - "Philomusean", 1921 (Box 30, Folder 55)
    - "The Bible", 1925 (Box 30, Folder 56)
    - "Fine Arts and Science Day", 1926 (Box 30, Folder 57)
    - "John Singer Sargent", 1926 (Box 30, Folder 58)
    - "Opportunities Presented by the Sesqui-Centennial in Arts and Education", 1926 (Box 30, Folder 59)
    - "Outlook for the Drama and the Theatre in America", 1926 (Box 30, Folder 60)
    - "Pennsylvania in Art", 1926 (Box 30, Folder 61)
    - Lecture on Murals, Bowdoin College, 1927 (Box 30, Folder 62)
    - "Mural Painting", 1927 (Box 30, Folder 63)
    - "Art", 1930 (Box 30, Folder 64)
    - "House of Wisdom", 1930 (Box 30, Folder 65)
    - "True Norm, The Carpenter's Square", 1932 (Box 30, Folder 66)
    - DuMaurier Lecture, 1933 (Box 30, Folder 67)
    - "50th Anniversary of Contemporary Club, 1886-1936", 1935 (Box 30, Folder 68)
    - "In Memorium, Jessie Willcox Smith", 1935 (Box 30, Folder 69)
    - "Mural Painting From the Mural Painter's Point of View", 1935-1936 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - On Sir Thomas Lawrence, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - "Sir Thomas Lawrence and the Tragic Muse", 1939 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - "Problems of a Mural Painter", 1939 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - "John Singer Sargent", 1940 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - "Place of Art in an Embattled World", 1940 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Summer Session of Cogslea Academy, 1940 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - "Edwin Austin Abbey", 1941 (Box 31, Folder 8-9)
    - "Island Idyll - Without Benefit of Electricity", 1941-1942 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Sir Edward Burne-Jones, 1942 (Box 31, Folder 11-12)
    - "Association of Students of D. Eloise Brownell", 1946 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - On Art and the Spiritual Life, 1947 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - "Art the Interpreter", 1948 (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - "Inspiration: Art and the Bible", 1949 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - Performances and Plays, 1908-1955; 3.4
    - "Armour of God", circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - "Dialogues of Emocles", circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - "First Dream", circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - "In Appreciation of the Engagement of the Kennedys at the Little Theatre", circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - "Power", circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - "Re-versal", circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - Notes and Subscriber List for the Little Theater, circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - History Pageant, 1908 (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - Theme for the Decorations in the Little Theatre, 1915-1916 (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Masque of Elsinore, 1918 (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - "Pageant of the National Academy", 1939 (Box 31, Folder 27)
    - "Prologue to the Play, "The Black Bear Inn, Devizes", 1939 (Box 31, Folder 28)
  - Poetry and Prose, 1915-1955; 3.5
    - Babylon's Streams, circa 1915-1955 (Box 31, Folder 29-32)
    - "An Allegory of Love", 1928-1929 (Box 31, Folder 33)
    - "Composition" (Albert Spalding), 1953 (Box 31, Folder 34)
  - Projects, Dante, 1915-1940; 3.6
    - Divine Comedy/Dante Window, 1915 (Box 31, Folder 35-37)
    - Notes on Dante and Divine Science, 1929 (Box 31, Folder 38)
    - Divine Comedy, Dramatic Reading, 1940 (Box 31, Folder 39)
    - Dante Lecture, 1940 (Box 31, Folder 40)
  - Projects, George Fox, 1955-1957; 3.7
    - Voice of George Fox: A Recording Transcribed, 1956 (Box 31, Folder 41)
    - Voice of George Fox, 1955-1957 (Box 31, Folder 42)
  - Projects, George Washington, 1934-1941; 3.8
    - Washington Notebook, 1934-1941 (Box 31, Folder 43)
    - The World in Washington, 1941 (Box 31, Folder 44)
  - Projects, Jane Addams, 1932-1943; 3.9
    - Jane Addams and Hull House, 1932 (Box 31, Folder 45)
    - Jane Addams Calendar, 1943 (Box 31, Folder 46)
    - Cathedral of Compassion, 1955 (Box 31, Folder 47-48)
  - Projects, Moses, 1928-1929; 3.10
    - Life of Moses, 1928-1929 (Box 31, Folder 49-50)
  - Projects, Samuel Morse, 1937-1939; 3.11
    - Dramatic Outline of the Life of Samuel F.B. Morse, 1937-1939 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Samuel F.B. Morse, 1937-1939 (Box 32, Folder 2-9)
  - Projects, William Penn, 1915-1955; 3.12
    - Bibliography of William Penn Works, circa 1915-1955 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - "Redemption of Penn's Charter", circa 1915-1955 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - "Penn's Experiment and the Pilgrimage of Peace", 1931 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - "Penn's Plan for Peace and Its Fulfillment in 1932", 1931 (Box 32, Folder 13-14)
    - "Proposed Programme in Celebration of 250 Years From 1682-1932" (Box 32, Folder 15-16)
    - Mighty Penn, A Masque of Peace, 1932 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Penn Memorial Fellowship, 1938 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Dramatic Outline of Life of William Penn, 1943 (Box 32, Folder 19)
    - "William Penn as Law Giver", 1951 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Projects, Caux Sur Montreaux, 1948-1949; 3.13
    - "Moral Re-Armament and A Renaissance of Arts", 1948 (Box 32, Folder 21)
    - Caux Sur Montreux, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 22-29)
    - "Caux Drawings", 1949 (Box 32, Folder 30)
    - "Experiences of an Artist at Caux", 1949 (Box 32, Folder 31)
    - "From William Penn to Caux", 1949 (Box 32, Folder 32)
  - Projects, First Presbyterian Church, 1930; 3.14
    - "Great Window of Healing", circa 1930 (Box 32, Folder 33)
    - Notes on "Windows of Heaven", 1930 (Box 32, Folder 34)
  - Projects, League of Nations, 1919-1957; 3.15
    - American Peace Plan, circa 1920-1955 (Box 32, Folder 35)
    - "League of Nations", circa 1920-1955 (Box 32, Folder 36)
    - Movement of Peace on Earth, circa 1920-1955 (Box 32, Folder 37)
    - League of Nations, 1919 (Box 32, Folder 38)
    - Geneva Calendar, 1927 (Box 32, Folder 39)
    - Geneva Journal, 1924-1927 (Box 32, Folder 40-41)
    - Notes From a Journal de Geneve, 1927 (Box 32, Folder 42)
    - Journal de Geneve (Part 1), 1927 (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
    - "Miracle of Geneva", 1927 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Miracle of Geneva, 1927 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Journal de Geneve (Part 2), 1928 (Box 33, Folder 5-7)
    - "Law Triumphant", 1928 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - "Thoughts in a Cathedral", 1928 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Notes From a Geneva Journal, 1929 (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Journal de Geneve (Part 3), 1929 (Box 33, Folder 11-13)
    - The Geneva Fellowship, 1929 (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - Miracle of Geneva/Journal de Geneve, 1927-1929 (Box 33, Folder 15-18)
    - Florentine Interlude, 1927-1929 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - Catalog of Drawings of the Delegates to League of Nations, 1929 (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - Miracle of Geneva/The Geneva Drawings, 1930-1932 (Box 33, Folder 21)
      Oversize material housed in Box 58.
    - Exhibition, Art Alliance of Philadelphia, 1930 (Box 33, Folder 22-23)
    - "Miracle of Geneva" (lectures), 1930-1931 (Box 33, Folder 24-28)
    - "Inner Light at Geneva", 1931 (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - Pennsylvania League of Nations, Membership Lists, 1932 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - "Christ at Geneva" (lecture), 1935 (Box 33, Folder 31)
    - Christ at Geneva (journal), 1936 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - "Christ at Geneva" (play), circa 1936 (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - Christ at Geneva, 1936 (Box 33, Folder 34)
    - Committee of Donors of the Geneva Drawings, 1936 (Box 33, Folder 35)
    - Geneva Journal, 1936 (Box 33, Folder 36-38)
    - Geneva and Rome, 1936-1937 (Box 33, Folder 39-40)
    - Second Report on the Geneva Drawings, 1936 (Box 33, Folder 41)
    - Speech in Geneva, 1936 (Box 33, Folder 42)
    - Christ at Geneva - The Divine Presence, 1937 (Box 33, Folder 43-44)
    - Excerpts from An Artist in Geneva, 1937 (Box 33, Folder 45)
    - Stronger Than Armies: Building of the City of God, 1938 (Box 33, Folder 46)
    - "Geneva and Rome", 1940 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - "Geneva and the Development of the League of Nations", 1942 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - "Miracle of Geneva" (lecture), 1942 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - "From William Penn to the United Nations", 1946 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - "Journal of an Artist at the United Nations", 1946 (Box 34, Folder 5-6)
    - "Making of the United Nations Drawings", 1946 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - "From William Penn to the United Nations", 1948-1949 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - The Coming of the City of God, 1950 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Group of United Nations Drawings, 1952 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - The Coming of the City of God, 1953 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - "250th Anniversary of the Coming of Willia Penn to His 'Holy Experiment' of Pennsylvania and in Honor of United Nations Week", 1957 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - "Majesty, Beauty, and Power of the Moral Law From Moses On", 1957 (Box 34, Folder 13-14)
    - Oversize Drafts of Miracle of Geneva/The Geneva Drawings from Box 33, Folder 21, 1930-1932 (Box 58)
  - Projects, Pennsylvania Capitol Murals, 1906-1960; 3.16
    - Founding of the State of Liberty Spiritual, 1906 (Box 34, Folder 15-18)
    - Founding of the State of Liberty Spiritual, 1906 (Box 34, Folder 19)
      Oversize materials housed in Box 59.
    - Mural Decorations for the Senate Chamber, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - Oxford Notes on Law, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 21-22)
    - Philosophy of Government, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 23-24)
    - "Philosophy of Government", circa 1912 (Box 34, Folder 25)
    - The Constitutional Convention, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 26)
    - The Federalist, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 27)
    - The Supreme Court, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 28)
    - Preliminary Notes for Holy Experiment, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 29)
    - Research Notebook, 1912 (Box 34, Folder 30)
    - Notes on the Constitutional Convention, 1915 (Box 34, Folder 31)
    - Philosophy of Government, Creation and Preservation of the Union, 1917 (Box 34, Folder 32)
    - Senate, 1917 (Box 34, Folder 33)
    - Senate Chamber, 1919 (Box 34, Folder 34)
    - Supreme Court Chamber, 1920 (Box 34, Folder 35)
    - Press Comments on Holy Experiment, 1920-1924 (Box 34, Folder 36)
    - Holy Experiment, 1921-1923 (Box 34, Folder 37)
    - Holy Experiment (typescript), 1922 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - Holy Experiment (draft), circa 1922 (Box 35, Folder 3-5)
    - Exhibition and Subscription Lists, Oxford University, 1923 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - "Pilgrimage with The Holy Experiment", 1923 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Book of Law, Supreme Court, 1926 (Box 35, Folder 8-11)
    - Holy Experiment, 1928 (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Lecture on Holy Experiment, 1929 (Box 35, Folder 13)
    - Lecture on Holy Experiment and Peace, 1929 (Box 35, Folder 14)
    - Lecture Notes, Lyceum of Florence, 1929 (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - Exhibition Catalog, Grand Central Galleries, 1930 (Box 35, Folder 16)
    - Law Triumphant, 1930 (Box 35, Folder 17)
    - The Law, 1931 (Box 35, Folder 18)
    - "Law Divine", circa 1931 (Box 35, Folder 19)
    - Law Triumphant, 1931 (Box 35, Folder 20-21)
    - Holy Experiment / Law Triumphant, 1931-1932 (Box 35, Folder 22)
    - Law Triumphant, 1931-1932 (Box 35, Folder 23-24)
    - Law Triumphant (subscriber lists), 1931-1932 (Box 35, Folder 25)
    - Law Triumphant - A Pageant of Peace, 1931-1932 (Box 35, Folder 26)
    - "Opening of the Book of Law", 1931-1932 (Box 35, Folder 27)
    - Law Triumphant, 1931-1933 (Box 35, Folder 28-30)
    - Lecture, Pennsylvania Literary Club, 1932 (Box 35, Folder 31-32)
    - Opening of the Book of Law, 1932 (Box 35, Folder 33-34)
      Oversize material housed in Boxes 60-61.
    - Law Triumphant, 1933 (Box 35, Folder 35)
    - Law Triumphant (subscriber lists), 1933 (Box 35, Folder 36)
    - Commission Preparatoire, 1934 (Box 35, Folder 37)
    - "Law Triumphant" Lecture, 1934 (Box 35, Folder 38)
    - "The Holy Experiment - Some Problems of a Mural Painter", 1940 (Box 35, Folder 39)
    - Pennsylvania Speaking!, 1942 (Box 35, Folder 40)
    - Holy Experiment (notes), 1944 (Box 36, Folder 1-4)
    - Holy Experiment (book drafts), circa 1944-1949 (Box 36, Folder 5-7)
    - Holy Experiment (book proofs), circa 1944-1949 (Box 36, Folder 8-10)
      Oversize material housed in Boxes 62-63 and OV 66 and OV 70.
    - Holy Experiment (subscription lists), 1944 (Box 36, Folder 11-12)
    - Holy Experiment (ad proofs and cover), 1952 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Oversize Draft of Founding of the State of Liberty Spiritual from Box 34, Folder 19, 1906 (Box 59)
    - Oversize Drafts of Opening of the Book of Law from Box 35, Folder 34, 1932 (Box 60-61)
    - Oversize Proofs of Holy Experiment from Box 36, Folder 10, circa 1944-1949 (Box 62-63)
    - Oversize Proofs of Holy Experiment from Box 36, Folder 10, circa 1944-1949 (Box OV 66, OV 70)
  - Projects, Pilgrimage of a Painter, 1944-1955; 3.17
    - Pilgrimage of a Painter (notes), 1944-1953 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - "Pilgrimage of a Painter", 1953 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Pilgrimage of a Painter (book draft), 1955 (Box 36, Folder 16)
  - Projects, Triptychs, 1941-1945; 3.18
    - Book of Triptychs, 1941-1945 (Box 36, Folder 17)
    - Army and Navy Triptychs, 1944 (Box 36, Folder 18)
  - Projects, Vassar Alumni House, 1924; 3.19
    - "Great Wonder", 1924 (Box 36, Folder 19)
      Oversize material housed in Box 64, Folder 1.
    - Overture Plan, 1924 (Box 36, Folder 20)
    - Oversize Proofs of "Great Wonder" from Box 36, Folder 19, 1924 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - Projects, Women of the Bible, 1945-1954; 3.20
    - Great Women of the Bible (book draft), 1945 (Box 36, Folder 21)
      Oversize material housed in Box 64, Folder 2.
    - Great Women of the Bible (notes), 1946-1948 (Box 36, Folder 22)
    - Great Women of the Bible, 1948-1949 (Box 36, Folder 23)
    - "Great Women of the Bible", 1954 (Box 36, Folder 24)
    - Oversize Draft of Great Women of the Bible from Box 36, Folder 21, 1945 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - Projects, Yarnall House, 1911; 3.21
    - "Building of the House of Wisdom", 1911 (Box 36, Folder 25)
  - Publications, 1915-1957; 3.22
    - Book Dummies 4-6, circa 1915-1955 (Box 36, Folder 26)
    - Christian Science Literature and Its Distribution, circa 1915-1955 (Box 36, Folder 27)
    - Christian Science Periodicals as Seen by an Artist, circa 1915-1955 (Box 36, Folder 28)
    - The Magic Table, circa 1915-1955 (Box 36, Folder 29)
    - Structure of the Second Church of Christ Scientist Philadelphia, 1917 (Box 36, Folder 30-31)
    - Brochures, Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 32)
    - American Field of Honor, 1920 (Box 36, Folder 33)
    - Appointed to Be Read in Churches, 1934 (Box 36, Folder 34)
    - Book of Remembrance, 1939 (Box 36, Folder 35)
    - Bookplates for the Cosmopolitan Club, 1941 (Box 36, Folder 36)
    - Faith at Work, 1957 (Box 36, Folder 37)
  - By Others, 1899-1976; 3.23
    - G.W.B.H., "At 'Red Rose'", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - E.S.L., "American Relief in Vienna", 1921 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Angell, Sir Norman, "What Was - And Is - "The Great Illusion?", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Armfield, Maxwell, "This Art Business", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Drummond, J. Roscoe, "Peace That Passeth Misunderstanding", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Emerson, Edith, Various Writings, 1906, 1976 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Jennings, W.B., "Poet's and Painter's Bibles", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Lethaby, W.R., Artistic Crafts Series of Technical Handbooks, 1915 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Marquess of Lothian, "Recovery", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Merrill, Margaret Bell, Poem, 1918 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Miller, Lewis Rex, "Looking Forward", 1934 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Oakley, Arthur, Poem, 1900 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Oakley, Hester, Poem (sonnet), 1899 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Raymond, W. Oakley, Various Writings, circa 1942-1956 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Richardson, "For the Wide Horizon", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Seymour, Violet, "Wheels", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Steele, Rufus, "Clipping the Wings of Fear", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - Wallace, Henry A., "World at the Crossroads", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - Wyllie, Philip, "Generation of Vipers", circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 19)
    - Author Unknown, circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, 1900-1975; 3.24
    - Chronological Miscellaneous, 1903-1925 (Box 37, Folder 21-33)
    - Chronological Miscellaneous, 1926-1935 (Box 37, Folder 34-43)
    - Chronological Miscellaneous, 1936-1945 (Box 37, Folder 44-54)
    - Chronological Miscellaneous, 1946-1955 (Box 37, Folder 55-64)
    - Chronological Miscellaneous, 1956-1975 (Box 37, Folder 65-70)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1915-1955 (Box 37, Folder 71-77)
      Oversize material housed in Box 64, Folder 3.
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1915-1955 (Box 38, Folder 1-11)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1915-1955 (Box 38, Folder 12-22)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1915-1955 (Box 38, Folder 23-33)
    - Oversize Miscellaneous from Box 37, Folder 71, circa 1915-1955 (Box 64, Folder 3)
- Diaries and Journals, 1891-1958; Series 4; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 38-39
  Materials are arranged in chronological order.
  Diaries and journals document Oakley's travels, research, notes on works. Some journals include sketches and enclosures such as cards, notes, and ephemera.
  - Journal/Notebook, circa 1915-1955 (Box 38, Folder 34)
  - Journals/Notebooks, 1891-1913 (Box 38, Folder 35-40)
  - Journals/Notebooks, 1915-1923 (Box 39, Folder 1-3)
  - Journal Enclosures, 1923 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Journals/Notebooks, 1924-1925 (Box 39, Folder 5-6)
  - Journal Enclosures, 1924-1925 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Journals/Notebooks, 1928-1952 (Box 39, Folder 8-13)
  - Journals/Notebooks, 1953-1958 (Box 39, Folder 14-21)
- Financial Material, 1874-1977; Series 5; 3.1 Linear feet Boxes 39-42
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  Financial materials include a card catalog of annotated artworks, artwork price lists, Cogslea studio publication costs and sales, subscriber and membership lists, and accounting records tracking home expenses for Oakley's studios and homes. These include monthly tracking sheets that split the home expenses shared by Oakley, Elizabeth Shippen Green, and Jessie Willcox Smith at the Cogslea studio and estate.
  - Artwork, 1915-1981; 5.1
    - Account Book for Classes Taught by Violet Oakley, 1953-1955 (Box 39, Folder 22)
    - Account Book for Cogslea Studio Publications, 1949-1952 (Box 39, Folder 23)
    - Account Ledger for "Great Wonder", 1925-1930 (Box 39, Folder 24)
    - Account Ledgers for "Holy Experiment", 1923-1926 (Box 39, Folder 25-26)
    - Artworks and Price List, circa 1915-1950 (Box 39, Folder 27)
    - Artwork Card File, circa 1920-1950 (Box 40, Folder 1-3)
    - Copyright Record, circa 1920-1955 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Record of Book Sales, 1950-1981 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Artwork, Lists, 1915-1950; 5.2
    - Cogslea Studio Publications List, 1939 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Emerson Publishing Society List, 1923 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Membership/Names, Distinguished Daughters of Pennsylvania, 1959 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Membership, Distinguished Daughters of Pennsylvania, 1953-1959 (Box 40, Folder 9-10)
    - Membership List, Cosmopolitan Club, circa 1920-1955 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - Membership Nominees, Philadelphia Museum, 1957 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Mural Painter's Portfolio Mailing Lists, 1950 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - Name List (Morse?), circa 1920-1955 (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - Name Lists, circa 1920-1955 (Box 40, Folder 15-20)
    - Portraits Owned by R.L. Taylor, circa 1920-1950 (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - Subscriber Lists, 1920 (Box 40, Folder 22-23)
    - Woodmere Patrons List, 1964-1967 (Box 40, Folder 24)
  - Home Expenses, 1891-1955; 5.3
    - Acount Book/Ledger, 1891-1892 (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Account Book for Violet Oakley, 1927-1929 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Checkbook for Violet Oakley, 1902-1903 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Account Book for Cornelia Oakley, 1895-1897 (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Bank Deposit Receipts for Violet Oakley, 1921-1927 (Box 41, Folder 5-6)
    - Checkbooks for Cornelia Oakley, 1900-1906 (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Domestic Help, 1925-1926 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - House Account Books for Violet Oakley, Elizabeth Shippen Green, Jessie Willcox Smith, and Henrietta Cozens, 1903-1918 (Box 41, Folder 9-10)
    - House Expenses for Violet Oakley, Elizabeth Shippen Green, Jessie Willcox Smith, and Henrietta Cozens, 1902-1913 (Box 41, Folder 11-12)
    - Inventory of Property, circa 1920-1955 (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1915-1955 (Box 41, Folder 14-15)